Allen Varley Astin Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Allen Varley Astin Papers1939-1973 (bulk 1950-1970)
MSS62002
Astin, Allen Varley, 1904-1984
25,000 items 66 containers 26 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Physicist and director, National Bureau of Standards. Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, agenda, reports, studies, congressional testimony, writings, speeches, conference papers, university teaching and training course records, research data, printed matter, and photographs documenting Astin's career at the National Bureau of Standards, 1928-1969.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Astin, Allen Varley, 1904-1984.; Astin, John.
Organizations
United States. National Bureau of Standards.; United States. Office of Scientific Research and Development.
Subjects
Bombardment.; Electric apparatus and appliances.; Electric insulators and insulation.; Electrification.; Metric system.; Ordnance.; Proximity fuzes.; Science and state--United States.; Science--International cooperation.; Telemeter.; Weights and measures.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.; World War, 1939-1945--England--London.
Places
Great Britain--Armed Forces.
Occupations
Physicists.; Public officials.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Allen Varley Astin, physicist and director of the National Bureau of Standards, were given to the Library of Congress in 1986 by his widow, Margaret Mackenzie Astin.
Additional Guides
A description of the Allen Varley Astin Papers appeared in
Library of Congress Acquisitions: Manuscript Division, 1986, p. 55.
Transfers
Audiotapes and motion picture films have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Allen Varley Astin are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1904, June 12 Born, Salt Lake City, Utah
1925 B.S. in physics, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah
1926 M.S. in physics, New York University, New York, N.Y. Chemical analyst, American Smelting and Refining Co., Salt Lake City, Utah
1927 Married Margaret Linnie Mackenzie
1928 Ph.D. in physics, New York University, New York, N.Y.
1928-1930 National Research Council Fellow, National Bureau of Standards Research Fellow, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.
1930-1932 Research associate, Utilities Research Commission, National Bureau of Standards
1932 Associate scientist, Electricity Division, National Bureau of Standards
1936 Physicist, Electricity Division, National Bureau of Standards
1940 Senior physicist, National Bureau of Standards
1943 Chief, Optical Fuse Section, Ordnance Development Division, National Bureau of Standards
1944 Assistant Chief, Ordnance Development Division, National Bureau of Standards
1944-1945 United States representative on proximity fuses in London, England, Office of Scientific Research and Development, Defense Department
1948 Chief, Ordnance Development Division, National Bureau of Standards
1950 Associate Director, National Bureau of Standards
1951 Acting Director, National Bureau of Standards
1952-1969 Director, National Bureau of Standards
1984, Jan. 28 Died, Bethesda, Md.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Allen Varley Astin (1904-1984) span the years 1921-1984 with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1950-1970. The collection is organized into three series. The National Bureau of Standards series documents Astin's forty-year career at the bureau, most especially his role as director, 1952-1969. The Professional Activities series documents his association with scientific, academic, governmental, and public administration organizations. A small file concerning his term as acting assistant secretary for science and technology at the Commerce Department is combined with a few family and personal papers into a Miscellany series.
The National Bureau of Standards series relates to all phases of Astin's career, including his earliest scientific research in measurement techniques for dielectric (electric insulating) materials, telemetering, and electronic instrumentation. Since the National Bureau of Standards was founded in 1901 to coincide with the electrification of American industry, Astin's initial research was among the work most emphasized at the bureau. During World War II, ordnance research dominated its program, and Astin was one of the scientists assembled at the bureau in 1940 to develop proximity fuses for bombs and rockets. In 1944 and 1945, he represented the bureau in London working in liaison with the Office of Scientific Research and Development and the British armed forces. Astin's proximity fuse file chiefly documents technical and tactical matters, yet reference is also made to the strategic decision not to use proximity fuses in Europe and to their limited use in the Burma and China.
Astin's papers also document his active leadership in the formulation of public policy relating to science. The National Bureau of Standards series provides a record of his influence, including his role in the controversy over negative findings on the battery additive marketed as "AD-X2." Dismissed by Secretary of Commerce Sinclair Weeks, Astin was exonerated by a scientific council appointed by President Dwight D. Eisenhower and overseen by the National Academy of Sciences. A subsequent report to the Secretary of Commerce made recommendations, which Astin helped to develop, for a reorganization of the National Bureau of Standards which eliminated ordnance research from its program and emphasized its primary role in establishing measurement standards and reliable properties of materials. Documentation for the AD-X2 controversy is located principally in the administrative file of the series.
Eisenhower approved the committee recommendations, reinstated Astin, and transferred the ordnance program to the Defense Department. Two new laboratories were then established by Defense: the Harry Diamond Laboratory in Washington, D.C., and the Corona Laboratory in California. Astin's association with these laboratories is documented in the Professional Activities series. Reorganization and relocation of the bureau to Gaithersburg, Maryland, is documented in the administrative file of the National Bureau of Standards series. In addition, the publications file in the same series includes Astin's 1968 interview for the Columbia University oral history of the Eisenhower administration and a draft manuscript for the bicentennial history of the bureau, "Measures of Assurance," both of which treat the AD-X2 controversy and bureau reorganization. Some of Astin's 1953 speeches in the National Bureau of Standards series also refer to the controversy.
Public speaking and publication files in the National Bureau of Standards series document Astin's articulation of the bureau's mission to governmental, scientific, and civic groups throughout the country and at European and Asian conferences. His extensive involvement in scientific associations, documented in the Professional Activities series, reflects the rise of late-twentieth-century research by committee and Astin's influence on the agenda of research programs in private and public laboratories. Other files in the Professional Activities series concern his efforts in scientific panels and governmental committees to define an autonomous role for scientists in public service.
Papers documenting Astin's role in international matters include the International Committee on Weights and Measures file in the National Bureau of Standards series and files for his work with State Department cooperative science programs in France and Japan in the Professional Activities series. Astin initiated studies at the bureau which were used in support of the Metric Conversion Act of 1975. The United States Metric Board file in the Professional Activities series documents his later work on national conversion.
Several letters and a few school and theatrical papers in the Miscellany series pertain to Astin's son, the actor John Astin, who is known for his portrayal of "Gomez" on the 1960s television show, "The Addams Family."
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in three series:
National Bureau of Standards, 1921-1983
Professional Activities, 1928-1984
Miscellany, 1934-1984
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm87062002
Container List
- National Bureau of Standards, 1921-1983 (Box 1-27)
  Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, agendas, reports, studies, congressional testimony, printed matter, photographs, writings, speeches and conference papers, research data, university teaching and in-house training course records, and other material from Astin's career with the bureau.
  Organized alphabetically by subject or type of material and chronologically thereunder.
  - Administrative files, Office of the Director (Box 1)
    - AD-X2 battery additive controversy
      - Correspondence, memoranda, and miscellany, 1952-1961, undated
      - "Report of the Committee on Battery Additives of the National Academy of Sciences," 1953, (7 folders); (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - "Report to the Secretary of Commerce," Ad Hoc Committee for Evaluation of Present Functions and Operations of National Bureau of Standards, 1953
    - Appointment
      - Letters of congratulations, 1951-1952, (2 folders)
      - Memoranda, clippings, and miscellany, 1951-1952
      - Swearing in ceremony, circa 1952
    - Authorizing legislation and orders, 1950-1968
    - Biographies, 1962-1969, undated
    - Boulder, Colo., laboratory, 1954-1961, undated
    - Budget
      - Planning documents, 1966-1967, undated
      - Statements, 1967-1969
    - Building research, 1962-1964, undated
    - "Century 21 Exposition," Seattle, Wash., 1958-1962 (Box 3)
    - Conferences, 1952-1969, undated
    - Condon, Edward U.
      - Banquet to honor, 1951
      - Correspondence and clippings, 1952-1968
    - Congressional testimony, 1955-1969, undated
    - Curtis, Harvey Lincoln, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Diary, Apr.-Sept. 1954
    - Executive leadership programs, 1962-1964
    - Executive personality analysis, 1954
    - International Bureau of Weights and Measures, Sevres, France, 1958-1967, undated
    - International cooperation
      - General, 1956-1968, undated, (2 folders)
      - USSR, 1956-1966, undated
  - Administrative files, Office of the Director (Box 5)
    - Memoranda
      - Commerce Department, 1953-1968, undated
      - Interoffice, 1950-1969, undated, (2 folders)
    - Mission statement and goals, 1963-1965, undated
    - Oddities, 1955-1964, undated, (2 folders)
    - Photographs (Box 6)
      - Award presentations, dinners, 1951-1969, undated
      - Meetings, groups, and visitors, 1953-1970, undated
      - Portraits, circa 1950-1970, undated
      - Miscellaneous persons and places, 1955, undated
    - Relocation to Gaithersburg, Md. (Box 7)
      - Dedication week ceremonies
        - Open house printed matter, 1966, undated
        - Photographs, 1966, undated, (4 folders)
      - Miscellaneous, 1961-1969
    - Reports, 1947-1969, undated (Box 8)
    - Retirement, 1969, undated
      - Boulder, Colo., activities
      - Correspondence, (2 folders)
      - Gaithersburg, Md., activities, (2 folders)
      - Printed matter
    - Science policy, 1951-1967, undated (Box 9)
    - Semicentennial, 1951
    - Studies
      - Research support to universities, 1960-1967
      - Scientific institutions, 1968-1969, (2 folders)
      - Scientific personnel
        - General, 1953-1968, undated, (2 folders)
        - National Bureau of Standards, 1953-1966, undated
    - Telephone directories, 1950-1956 (Box 10)
  - Awards, commendations, and honors
    - Civil Service League, Career Service Award, 1960
    - Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineering, Harry Diamond Award, 1970
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1945-1967
    - Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., Rockefeller Public Service Award, 1963
  - General correspondence
    - 1949-1954, (2 folders)
    - 1955-1970, undated, (5 folders) (Box 11)
  - Personnel records (Astin), 1935-1960
  - Publications (Box 12)
    - About Astin, clippings and offprints, 1949-1968
    - By Astin
      - Copies and offprints, 1931-1969, undated, (4 folders)
      - Drafts and related material
        - 1948-1952, miscellaneous
        - 1954
          - "The IEC and the National Bureau of Standards," Magazine of Standards
          - "Physical Standards and Industrial Progress," for proposed book
        - 1958, "Standardization of the Inch"
        - 1959
          - "An Atomic Standard for Length Measurement," Engineer's News Supplement, New York Herald Tribune Co.
          - Statement, Encyclopedic Dictionary of Electronics and Nuclear Engineering
        - 1960, "Miniaturization -- A New Science," preface for proposed book (Box 13)
        - 1961-1966, miscellaneous
        - 1967, "Measurement Accuracy at Radio Frequencies," proceedings of the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers
        - 1968
          - Oral history transcript, Eisenhower Administration Project, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
          - "A Time for Action in International Standardization," Materials Research and Standards
          - "Voluntary Standardization and the Government: Fifty Years of Cooperation," Magazine of Standards
        - 1969, "Management and the Metric System," Defense Management Journal
        - 1981-1983, Commerce Department oral history project
        - Undated
    - About the National Bureau of Standards
      - Clippings, offprints and reprints, 1951-1966, undated
      - Official brochures and pamphlets
        - 1925-1951, (2 folders)
        - 1952-1969, (2 folders) (Box 14)
      - "Measures of Assurance: A History of the National Bureau of Standards, 1951-1976," typescript for comment, 1972-1976, (3 folders)
    - By National Bureau of Standards staff
      - Printed matter, 1921-1975, (2 folders)
      - Typescripts, 1938-1976, (4 folders) (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1930-1968, undated, (2 folders)
  - Research records
    - Correspondence, 1936-1949
    - Data
      - Negative power factor, 1938
      - Unidentified, undated
    - Electronic computers section (Box 16)
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1949-1951, undated
      - Reports, 1947-1950
    - "Handbook of Physical Measurement"
      - "Electricity" volume
        - Introduction, 1946, undated
        - "Power and Energy" chapter, undated
      - Outline, 1947
    - Induction and capacitance section reports, 1939-1940
    - Ordnance Development Division
      - Memoranda, 1946-1947
      - Research
        - Arctic Test Detachment, United States Army, Ft. Churchill, Manitoba, Canada, 1948-1949
        - General, 1954-1958, undated
    - Proximity fuse
      - Diamond, Harry, 1945-1949, undated
      - Miscellaneous photographs and printed matter, 1945-1947, undated
      - Office of Scientific Research and Development, London Mission
        - Correspondence and memoranda, 1943-1946, 1959
        - Notes, undated
        - Photographs, field tests, undated
        - Reports, 1944-1945, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Speeches, lectures, and conference records
    - Nov. 1950-Nov. 1951, (5 folders)
    - 1952
      - Apr.-Nov., (8 folders)
      - Dec., (2 folders) (Box 18)
      - Miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - 1953
      - Jan.-Nov., (12 folders)
      - Dec. (Box 19)
      - Miscellaneous
    - 1954, Feb.-Nov., (19 folders)
    - 1955, Jan.-Nov., (15 folders) (Box 20)
    - 1956
      - Feb.-June, (9 folders)
      - Sept.-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 21)
      - Miscellaneous
    - 1957, Jan.-Dec., (9 folders)
    - 1958
      - Jan.-May, (5 folders)
      - June-Dec., (6 folders) (Box 22)
      - Miscellaneous
    - 1959, Jan.-Oct., (15 folders)
    - 1960, Apr.-Nov. 1962, (19 folders) (Box 23)
    - 1963, Feb.-Nov. 1965, (11 folders) (Box 24)
    - 1966, Jan.-Dec., (17 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1967, Feb.-Sept. 1969, (20 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1970, Dec.-Sept. 1971, (5 folders) (Box 27)
    - Undated
      - Miscellaneous
      - USSR, conference
  - Training courses
    - Electromagnetic theory
      - George Washington University, Washington, D.C., 1941-1942
      - Miscellaneous, 1937-1946, undated
    - Vector analysis and electrostatics, 1939
- Professional Activities, 1928-1984 (Box 28-61)
  Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, agendas, business records, notes, reports, studies, printed matter, photographs, and other records from Astin's committee work with various organizations.
  Arranged alphabetically by title of the organization, institution, agency, or commission and thereunder by subject or document type.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 28)
    - Committee on Scientific Freedom and Responsibility, notes and background material, undated
    - Correspondence, 1970-1974, (2 folders)
    - Memoranda, 1970-1973
    - Minutes, 1971-1973
    - Printed matter
      - Guidelines and codes of ethics for professional employment, 1960-1973, undated, (3 folders)
      - Miscellaneous, 1969-1974, undated, (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - Reports, 1967-1974, (4 folders)
  - American National Standards Institute
    - Correspondence, 1969-1970
    - Long-range Planning Committee
      - Agenda and minutes, 1969-1970
      - Correspondence, memoranda, and miscellany, 1965-1971, undated, (4 folders) (Box 30)
    - Reports, 1969-1970
  - American Ordnance Association, 1951-1952
  - American Philosophical Society
    - Committee on Meetings, 1980-1983
    - Correspondence, 1971-1983
    - Meeting programs, 1958, 1977-1983
    - Membership nominations, 1972-1984, undated (Box 31)
    - Memoranda, 1977-1983, undated
    - Printed matter, 1975-1980
  - American Physical Society, 1928, 1953-1959
  - American Society for Testing and Materials
    - Annual meeting, Atlantic City, N.J., 1971
    - Committees, 1971
    - Computerization of laboratory instruments, 1969-1970
    - Correspondence, 1963-1971
    - Executive Committee awards, 1965-1971
    - Fire tests, 1970-1971
    - Forensic science, 1969-1972 (Box 32)
    - Minutes, 1970-1973
    - Reports and statements, 1967-1972
    - Tire tests, 1969-1972
  - Applied Mathematics Advisory Council, 1948-1950
  - Commission on Government Procurement, Research and Development Study Group, 1969-1973, (3 folders)
  - Defense Science Board, 1960-1964, (2 folders) (Box 33)
  - Environmental Protection Agency, oversight hearings, 1978-1979
  - Federal Council for Science and Technology, Civil Service Commission
    - Federal executive service, 1962-1973
    - National Medal of Science Award Committee, 1962-1968
    - Printed matter
      - Miscellaneous, 1966-1970, (2 folders)
      - Reports, 1954-1971 (Box 34)
    - Symposia, 1963-1968, (2 folders)
  - Franklin Institute, Philadelphia, Pa.
    - Printed matter, 1970-1974
    - Research Review Committee, 1974-1976
  - George Washington University Center for Measurement Science, Washington, D.C., 1962-1967, (2 folders) (Box 35)
  - Harry Diamond Laboratories, Scientific Advisory Committee, 1955-1967
  - Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineering
    - Correspondence, 1956-1983
    - Field Awards Committee, 1973-1974
    - Memoranda
      - 1978-1981, (2 folders)
      - 1982-1983, (4 folders) (Box 36)
    - Reports, 1971-1983, (2 folders)
    - Speeches and statements, 1976-1979
  - International Atomic Energy Agency (Box 37)
    - Draft report, 1971-1972, (3 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1970-1983
    - Panel to reexamine the relationship of the United States to, 1962-1972
    - Study group meetings
      - 21 June-7 July 1971, (2 folders)
      - 16 July 1971 (Box 38)
  - Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md., 1958-1969
  - National Academy of Public Administration
    - Agenda, 1968-1972
    - Colloquium on reorganization, 1970
    - Correspondence, 1968-1982
    - Effective departmental management conference, 1969
    - Meetings, 1969-1982
    - Memoranda, 1968-1983, (5 folders) (Box 39)
    - Minutes, 1969-1973, (3 folders)
  - National Academy of Public Administration (Box 40)
    - Miscellany, 1969-1980, undated, (2 folders)
    - Printed matter, 1972-1979, undated
    - Reports, 1970-1983
    - Technology assessment, 1970-1973, (3 folders)
  - National Academy of Sciences (Box 41)
    - Advisory Committee to the Department of Housing and Urban Development, 1974
    - Auditing Committee, 1963-1967, 1982-1983
    - Biographical Memoirs Committee
      - Assignments
        - Correspondence, 1971-1972
        - Lists, 1971, undated
        - Suggestions, 1971, undated
      - Bocher, Maxime, notes, 1971, undated
      - Foote, Paul D.
        - Notes, 1953-1974, undated
        - Text, 1972-1979, undated
    - Building Research Advisory Board, 1971-1975 (Box 42)
    - Business meetings, 1970-1975, (3 folders)
    - Bylaws Committee
      - General, 1965-1974, undated
      - Proposed amendments, 1971-1973, undated, (2 folders) (Box 43)
    - Cochrane, Rexmond C., centennial history, 1974
    - Copernicus quincentenary, nature of scientific discovery symposium, 1972-1973
    - Council meetings, 1972-1975
    - Criteria of Success in Science conference, Washington, D.C., 1953
    - General correspondence, 1957-1971, 1981-1983
    - Election ballots, 1978-1982 (Box 44)
    - Membership Committee
      - Age distribution studies, 1969-1975, undated
      - Class memberships, 1967-1975, undated, (2 folders)
      - Elections (Box 45)
        - Ballot reports, 1973-1975, undated, (2 folders)
        - Procedures, 1970-1973
      - Nominations, 1974-1975
      - Quotas, 1970-1974, undated
    - Motor Vehicle Emissions Committee, 1972-1973
    - National Academy of Engineering, joint operation of the National Research Council, 1970-1971, (3 folders)
    - National Bureau of Standards advisory panels, 1964 (Box 46)
    - Office of the Home Secretary, memoranda and notices, 1970-1975, undated
    - Science and public policy, 1970-1975, (2 folders)
    - Shockley, William
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Genetic Factors in Human Performance, 1969-1971, (2 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1957-1967
      - Proposed resolution for annual meeting, 1972 (Box 47)
    - SST-Supersonic Boom Committee, 1968-1970
    - Trust Fund, 1966-1975, undated
  - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, 1952-1958
  - National Aeronautics and Space Administration, 1969-1973
  - New York University, New York, N.Y., 1952-1960, 1981-1983
  - Organization of Applied Research in Europe, 1954-1956
  - Pacific Science Center Foundation, Seattle, Wash.
    - 1962-1966, (2 folders)
    - 1967-1972 (Box 48)
  - Science Service, Inc., Washington, D.C.
    - Board of Trustees, 1966-1972, (4 folders)
    - Science News Advisory Committee, 1967-1972 (Box 49)
      - (2 folders)
  - State Department, Bureau of International Scientific and Technological Affairs
    - United States-France Cooperative Program
      - Consultant, 1976-1977
      - Coordinator
        - General
          - 1969-1971, (4 folders)
          - 1972-1973, (5 folders) (Box 50)
          - 1974-1975, (4 folders) (Box 51)
        - Trips, 1970-1976, (3 folders)
      - Facilities inventory reports, 1971, (2 folders) (Box 52)
      - Printed matter, 1964-1974, (3 folders)
    - United States-Japan Committee on Scientific Cooperation (Box 53)
      - Liaison
        - 1961-1967, (6 folders)
        - 1969-1970, (5 folders) (Box 54)
        - 1971, (5 folders) (Box 55)